Today's דף daf. *Daf* is דף ל"ט *Daf Lammed Tet*. We pick
up at the middle of, at the first wide line of ל"ח
עמוד ב' *Lammed Chet Amud Bet*. So we're just a little bit
wrapping up the previous דף *Daf*. המשנה *Hamishnah* introduced two different, two
new types of ovens: the תנור Tannur. *Tannur*, which is the pyramidal
type of oven which is used for baking bread, which is much
stricter even if you use the קש *Kash* and the גבבה *Gvava*
and even if there are no coals to stir, it's forbidden; and
the כופח *Kupach*, which is a middle position. And anyway, the discussion
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* has is: what about, is this תנור Tannur
*Tannur* you allowed to—is it so strict that you can't even put
something up against the side of it? We talked the other day
that a כירה Kira *Kira*, even if it has the burning fire,
you can put something on the outside against it. What's the story
with a תנור Tannur *Tannur*? And אביי *Abaye* said it was forbidden.
So we pick up with that. תניא כוותיה דאביי
*Tanya Kevateh de-Abaye*, we taught like אביי *Abaye*. תנור שהסיקוהו בקש ובגבבה
*Tannur she-sikuhu be-kash u-ve-gvava*, if a תנור *Tannur* was lit a
flame, they made the fire with the straw and stubble,
so normally that would be very lenient but with a תנור *Tannur*
it's not. אין סומכין לו *Ein somchin lo*, you cannot put something
nearby it, against it to heat up, ואין צריך לומר על גביו
*ve-ein tzarich lomar al gabav*, certainly you can't put something on top
of it, ואין צריך לומר לתוכו *ve-ein tzarich lomar le-tocho*, and certainly
how much more so can you not put something
inside of it, ואין צריך לומר בגפת ובעצים *ve-ein tzarich lomar be-gefet
u-ve-etzim*, if you use actual wood and sticks instead. Okay, but here
it's very explicit that you cannot put something up against a תנור
*Tannur* even on the outside, like אביי *Abaye*. כופח *Kupach*, now this
כופח *Kupach*, which is this middle type of an oven, it's somewhere
between a כירה Kira *Kira* and a תנור *Tannur*. שהסיקוהו בקש ובגבבה
*she-sikuhu be-kash u-ve-gvava*, so if you used straw and stubble then it
falls into the lenient category. סומכין לו *somchin lo*, you can put
stuff outside of it. Now, our גירסא *girsa* is ואין נותנין על
גביו *ve-ein notnin al gabav*, you can't put on top of it,
which would be true assuming you did not sweep it out. So
then we're talking even if you didn't sweep it out you could
put up against it, like the כירה Kira *Kira* even in an
exposed flame, but you cannot put on top of it or in
it. The גירסא *girsa* which is the גירסא *girsa* to ונותנין על
גביו *ve-notnin al gabav*, which would be case swept out. But anyway,
we're talking about an exposed flame, even though it's exposed, you can
put on the outside of it. That's if it's straw and stubble.
בגפת ובעצים *Be-gefet u-ve-etzim*, however,
if you used wood and wood chips, even presumably if it's swept
it out or if it's covered, it has הלכה Halacha *halacha* of
a תנור *Tannur*. And therefore, אין סומכין לו *ein somchin lo*, you
cannot put on the outside of it. So we see like אביי
*Abaye* that a תנור *Tannur* or כופח *Kupach* when it's like a
תנור *Tannur* because you used wood chips, then you cannot even put
stuff on the outside, it is so strict.
So what's the, what's the problem?
You think you're going to what exactly? Yeah, it's not exactly clear.
I mean, if there were wood chips, you'd be concerned that you'll
come to stir it even if you put some ashes on it.
But by a תנור *Tannur* we're strict even if it's just used
straw and stubble, so it
seems to be more like a מחזי כמבשל mechzi k'mevashel *mechzei ke-mevashel*
or לא פלוג *lo pelug*, it's not exactly clear. At that stage,
it stops being so clear what the concern is. אמר amar ליה
רב Rav אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי *Amar lei Rav Acha brei
de-Rava le-Rav Ashi*, Rav Acha the son of Rava said to Rav
Ashi: האי כופח היכי דמי *Hai kupach heichi dami*, what is exactly
the story of a כופח *Kupach*? היכי דמי *heichi dami*? אי ככירה
דמי *I ke-kira dami*, if it's like a כירה Kira, *Kira*, אפילו
בגפת ובעצים נמי *afillu be-gefet u-ve-etzim nami*, then it should be permissible
even if you used wood and sticks as long as you swept
it out. אי כתנור דמי *I ke-tannur dami*, if it's like a
תנור *Tannur*, אפילו בקש ובגבבה נמי לא *afillu be-kash u-ve-gvava nami lo*,
then even with straw and stubble it should be no go. Why
is it in this middle category? Why not? Well, okay, here's what
he's going to say. אמר Amar ליה *Amar lei*: נפיש הבליה מכירה
*nafish hevlei mi-kira*, it has greater heat, contained heat than a כירה
Kira. *Kira*, וזוטא הבליה מתנור *ve-zuta hevlei mi-tannur*, and it's less contained
heat than a תנור *Tannur*, so it's in a middle category. היכי
דמי כופח היכי דמי כירה Kira, *Heichi dami kupach heichi dami kira*?
So what is the physical difference of them, like structurally? אמר רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi ברבי חנינא *Amar Rabbi Yossi berabbi Chanina*: כופח מקום
שפיסת קדירה אחת *kupach mekom shfisas kdera achas*, כופח *Kupach* only has
a place for one קדירה *kdera*. So it's very much like a
very tight space and very contained heat.
כירה Kira *Kira*, most of their ovens as we saw were basically
shaped like essentially like a pot and you put a pot inside
of it. But anyway, it's only place for one pot.
Is this something they're familiar with?
Maybe not so much. One is a משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* in ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* and the other is a discussion in בבל *Bavel*.
So probably they weren't so familiar with it. כירה Kira. מקום שפיסת
שתי קדירות *Kira mekom shfisas shtei kderos*. So a כירה Kira. *Kira*
has a place for two pots and therefore, even though presumably those
two spots places were separated with a wall as we discussed the
other day, nevertheless, because it somehow is a larger thing, there's
greater airflow and it's not as hot. Okay, as we saw in
the pictures I handed out, it's not just a difference of one
pot and two pots. At least this is from a book that
is based on a real look at the, archeologically and whatever what
we know about the pottery vessels in the time of the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that a bigger difference, as we actually even saw the
other day, כירה *Kira* sometimes could be for one pot, sometimes would
be for two pots. A major difference seems to be more. that
the כירה had more like exposed walls or more just openness to
air, whereas a קופח Kupach was a very tight fit and the
heat was coming from the bottom through some holes at the bottom
and again it was very much more contained heat but the whole
difference was not whether it was a one spot one pot or
two spot or two pot spaces. What does he say then? I
don't know, maybe that is one of the differences, but I don't
know. אמר אביי ואיבעית אימא רבי ירמיה אף אנן נמי תנינא, Amar
Abaye ve-iba'it eima Rabbi Yirmiyah af anan nami tanina,
we taught similarly this idea that a כירה standard has two spaces
for two pots. כירה שנחלקה לאורכה טהורה, Kira she-nechelka le-orkah tehorah,
if a כירה was split in half lengthwise, if you imagine that
it's a lengthwise thing with like a double pot holder or like
you have these like double burner hot plates or whatever, it's a
lengthwise thing, so if you split it lengthwise then it's טהורה, tehorah,
right because then it's totally unusable, right because so then it's טהורה.
tehorah. לרחבה, Le-rochbah, if you split it widthwise then you have two
individual now כירות, Kirot, you have something that was side by side
spaces for pots, split in half you have now two individual כירות,
Kirot, then טמאה, teme'ah, it is טמא, tamei, so you see that
a standard
כירה has two separate holes for two separate pots. קופח בין לאורכה
בין לרחבה טהור, Kupach bein le-orkah bein le-rochbah tahor, קופח Kupach whether
lengthwise or widthwise is טהור tahor because only a space with one
spot and now however you split it it no longer is usable.
So that is the end of that משנה Mishnah, about the differences
between כירה, קופח, Kupach, and תנור. Yes.
So in dealing with stovetops today we model our הלכה למעשה Halacha
le-Ma'aseh on the כירה. You talked about modern ovens.
Well I mentioned that. So yesterday I mentioned that modern ovens the
basic consensus in the פוסקים Poskim is that our what we would
call תנור in modern Hebrew basically has the הלכה halakha, of כירה,
that there's a lot of there's a large open space, it's ventilated,
so it is not the I mean if you want to get
a sense of what is the type of a תנור that's like
a pizza oven where it's really an enormous amount of contained heat,
not ventilated and so on. So basically all the פוסקים Poskim assume
that our ovens have a status of a כירה which is a
good thing which allows for these various things.
Yeah I'm not complaining but they were talking about the level of
heat.
I understand. So yeah that's what it says. Yeah. Okay. And it
is true that our ovens although they do a good job
cooking they do have air space and ventilation and so on. It's
not the same as like a pizza oven. Right.
Some say like a כירה.
Right. Well I should mention now as because what we're about to
do right now actually is shift from so that was a lot
so we spent a good couple of intense days dealing with שהייה
וחזרה Shehiyah ve-Chazarah and now we're going to shift to the rest
of the פרק Perek really is going to be devoted to issues
of cooking in general like what constitutes cooking on שבת Shabbat and
not about the ערב שבת Erev Shabbat שהייה וחזרה. Shehiyah ve-Chazarah. So
we were discussing some of the הלכה למעשה Halacha le-Ma'aseh but one
thing that I should mention is all along I've been saying that
we do a translation of גרוף וקטום Garuf ve-Katum of swept out
or ashes put on as our modern
בלעך. Blech. Well because we were just now talking about what's the
translation of our modern oven we said כירה. So what's the translation
of גרוף וקטום Garuf ve-Katum our modern בלעך. Blech. Well it's somewhat
debatable why. Well before I get to why it's debatable let me
first of all point out that רב משה Rav Moshe already says
and רב עובדיה Rav Ovadia for different reasons that you could question
whether we need to do anything in our modern ovens. Maybe an
exposed flame should be totally okay. Why? So רב משה Rav Moshe
says for a technical reason. He says the concern in the גמרא,
Gemara what's our concern? Our concern is you'll adjust the knobs. That's
effectively meaning that you'll add more fuel. The גמרא Gemara was never
concerned you'll add more fuel, the גמרא Gemara was concerned you'll take
the existing ashes and you'll stir it, right? So this is a
different type of a concern. So maybe it doesn't fall into the
technical גזירה gezeirah and maybe it shouldn't be an issue altogether. Okay
maybe but it's irresponsible. Fine, you put some tape on the knobs
or whatever, but to try to put the demand the exact demands
of this תקנה Takkanah maybe he says technically it's not the same
reality because you're adding more fuel and in the גמרא Gemara it's
stirring the ashes. רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef says there's a
different reason to just say that it shouldn't apply because he says
we have a nice steady burning flame and maybe this is a
much more practical reason than a formalistic reason. In the גמרא Gemara.
you have wood and firewood whatever, it goes out and it's this
and that, you need to fiddle with it more. For us you
got the thing on you leave it alone. So maybe the concern
shouldn't exist. So both רב משה Rav Moshe and רב עובדיה Rav
Ovadia put right up front that you could argue in
theory that you don't need to do any of these requirements but
the reason that they make that point is because you could also
argue that what we are doing doesn't satisfy. Why is what we're
doing doesn't satisfy? Because what they did in the גמרא Gemara. was
they put something on the fire itself which actually lowered the heat
and caused the fire to be on its way of going out
even though sometimes it talked about what if it reignites but nevertheless
it was the beginning of the process of putting it out. Okay
what we do with the בלעך Blech or knob covers is even
though the בלעך Blech puts something on the heat and it somewhat
lowers the heat it doesn't sort of start the flame to go
out it only somewhat decreases the heat, right? So therefore you could
so it seems like they're sort of it's like the safety net
right up front before you start complaining that our בלעך Blech isn't
exactly what is
in the
גמרא. Gemara So why do our בלעכס blechs count? So here becomes
an interesting discussion of what do you need to satisfy the גמרא.
Gemara So some say you just have a piece of metal covering
the בלעך. blech. That does what the גמרא Gemara says, which is
it's something covering the heat, the heat source, like the ashes on
it. But some will say no, but in the גמרא Gemara. it
didn't just cover the heat source, it actually was a היכר, heker,
so if you were to come to stir, you would like see
that there's something different, there's ashes there and that would somehow be
a היכר. heker. Here where you're going to change the knobs is
not where the בלעך blech is. So therefore, so therefore some say,
okay, so therefore just have something on the knobs. Remove the knobs,
tape over the knobs, say ah, but maybe, but that doesn't, but
that, so then you've got a היכר heker where you'll come to
turn, but it's not covering the heat source. And in the גמרא
Gemara you had both. So the פרימסט frummest בלעך blech is, and
I don't know if you've seen these, a single piece of metal
that goes over the burners and then down over the knobs. So
it's the same thing that both covers the heat source and is
a היכר heker where you would come to adjust. And that they
say is the most comparable to the case in the גמרא. gemara
Nevertheless, for most, you know as I know, for
most פוסקים poskim feel that and most practice is that it's okay
just to cover the heat source, that's enough of a היכר. heker.
You'll see that when you're coming to turn the knob where the
knobs is, you'll still see that היכר heker and just covering the
heat source is enough. There are some who say, and רב Rav
what's his name from Lakewood, רב Rav Eider?
No, no, רב Rav
Abadi? No, no, from the previous generation. רב Rav Eider quotes him,
what? רב Rav Hutner? I think רב Rav Hutner, what? רב Rav
Aharon Kotler? רב Rav Aharon Kotler. רב Rav Eider quotes רב Rav
Aharon Kotler who says that it's sufficient just to remove the knobs
or just to put a סימן siman on the knobs, that you
don't have to put something on the heat source, it's enough to
put a סימן siman where you'll come to adjust it and it's
enough to put it on the knobs. And that leads to an
interesting question about things that are naturally have the heat source covered,
like a crockpot, right? So should you put another covering on an
already existing covering? You can't just say, oh, you're totally fine because
there's no היכר, heker, there's nothing. So what do you do by
crockpots? So some people put a liner of tin foil on the
inside to do another covering on an already covered source. But then
it creates problems because then it's like הטמנה hatmana because then it
keeps the pot very tight. We haven't gotten הטמנה hatmana yet. So
what I do is in those situations I just rely
on רב Eider and I just cover the knobs in the type
in the crockpot scenario because the heat's already covered. And even though
there's no היכר heker on the covering of it, then you just
cover the knobs and you're okay. But there are interesting questions, and
there also modernly there are these modern stovetops that are like these
total glass stovetops where the burners are totally covered. So what do
you do when it's already covered? Do you put a cover on
the cover? Should you just cover the knobs? So that raises that
question over there. But that's the modern translation of what we have
been doing. And just as long as we're wrapping it up, just
to remind us of what the conclusion was the other day. So
when it comes to leaving stuff on the flame from before שבת,
Shabbos, so there the אשכנזים Ashkenazim in principle פסקן pasken like חנניה
Chananaya that once it's already partially cooked, half or a third or
whatever, you can really in theory leave it on a completely exposed
flame before שבת. Shabbos. If you're just leaving it and not going
to put it back, that's in theory. In practice, I don't find
too many people that are doing that. Anyway, לכתחילה lechat'chila we try
to be מחמיר machmir like the other position, which is like the
ספרדי Sefardi position, which is as long as the food is even
if it's fully cooked until it gets to a point of מצטמק
ורע לו mitsamek v'ra lo that continued cooking makes it bad, then
you require to cover the flame. That's the ספרדי Sefardi position. In
terms of putting it back, everybody agrees that if you want to
take it off and put it back, you need to have a
covered flame. And then the question is is that what constitutes חזרה
hazara like it's in taking off and still in the process of
coming back, an uninterrupted process? And that we discussed yesterday. Holding it,
having in mind to put it back, לכתחילה lechat'chila you need both
of those criteria. בדיעבד bediavad the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah says one
would be enough. Also maybe putting on the counter would be equivalent
to holding in the hand. Can you be סומך somech on that?
The משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah says sometimes if you need to you
can. And then the final question, which is the big question, is
what do you need to put it straight from the refrigerator שבת
Shabbos morning, which is no-go לכתחילה. lechat'chila. So certainly you need that
the food be dry and not wet because then it's a בישול
bishul problem or it be fully cooked, right? Then otherwise you'd be
a בישול bishul problem. And what would constitute there that it's not
מחזי כמבשל when you put it straight from the fridge? So there
we discussed that in a context where it really is not at
all like cooking. So putting it on like a hot plate where
nobody cooks on a hot plate, that could be okay. Putting it
on a בלעך, blech,
that אשכנזים Ashkenazim still feel is enough like cooking when you're going
straight out of the fridge. But some ספרדים Sefardim פסקן pasken that
even a בלעך blech is okay if you're doing it straight from
the refrigerator. Yes.
When are you going to get to the
קדרה בלעך?
kedera blech? All right, I'll just mention that for a second, but
then we'll go on. This is again like a great example of
formalism trumping real issues. There's another possibility that's mentioned here, not mentioned
here, mentioned in the ראשונים Rishonim as a way you can take
stuff and be נותן לכתחילה, nosein l'chatchila, which is not דרך בישול,
derech bishul, which is putting something on top of a pot that's
on the stove. I've got my soup cooking on the stove, okay,
and I go ahead and I put something on top of the
soup pot. So again, something's already cooked, it's not a בישול bishul
concern, it's just a looks like it's cooking נותן לכתחילה. nosein l'chatchila.
Can I put it? So therefore the רבינו יונה, Rabbeinu Yonah, the
רשב"א Rashba I believe says that that case it's all right, it's
so not a normal way to cook to put something on top
of a soup pot. So they say it has to have stuff
in it. If it didn't have stuff in it, it would just
be like putting it on a בלעך, blech, just putting it on
top of cement, but you're putting it on something that's already cooking.
So comes along some genius a few years ago and develops this
thing that I don't know what he's called, what did you call
it? The קדירה בלעך. Kedera Blech. I've heard it called the אן-בלעך
unblech anyway, it's basically an entire בלעך, blech, but it's like really
inside of it got a very thin hollow inside of it where
it has water. So you basically what they call this is a
long thin pot. So you put this on right because it's got
water inside of it. So you put it on the stovetop so
now you've got a pot cooking on the stove so you put
something on it so it's not דרך בישול. derech bishul. I mean
if דרך בישול derech bishul is addressing an experiential reality, that does
not change anything from a real בלעך, blech, but that's like a
nice example of people formalizing things that are supposed to be
normally cook on a בלעך. blech.
Okay, so if you want to say a בלעך blech is לאו
דרך בישול lav derech bishul like רב עובדיה Rav Ovadia says it,
but you know how it helps by having water on the inside
that nobody can see. But they still need to have hot water.
What? No, you don't need to have hot water.
You don't use it. It's sealed. Sealed. But there is one type
that my daughter's father-in-law has that has like 20 rabbis' הסכמות haskamas
and you... it's a בלעך, blech, it's electric, and it's also a
hot pot, an urn. So you have this part also with water
and then the entire top... interesting. But it goes on the stovetop?
No, so it's basically like a hot plate. Okay fine, but a
hot plate
I understand.
Okay, but you wouldn't need the water part. I feel that if
it's a hot plate that nobody ever cooks on and it's not
then you could use it straight to put from the fridge.
Someone says not everyone necessarily says
it needs a cover... why would that be?
No, either an אן-בלעך unblech either you have to cover the knobs
or you have to fill the inside with thin oil. You can't
do nothing because then it's דרך בישול. derech bishul.
Like a plastic, a plastic insulator.
No, that's still דרך בישול, derech bishul, that's how you cook in
a crock pot. Okay. All right, so now we're going to move
on. So that's what we're saying for now about שהייה shehiya and
חזרה. chazara. Now we move on to talking about straight cooking issues.
אין נותנין ביצה בצד המיחם בשביל שתתגלגל. Ain nosnin beitsa b'tzad hameicham
bishvil shetitgalgel. So now we're not ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, we're on
שבת. Shabbat. You cannot put an egg by the side of a
water heater
in order that it should that it should hard boil, that it
should, that it should cook. Okay, and presumably you could do that,
eggs cook relatively easily, you put it against something that's filled with
hot water on the fire and it'll cook. You're not allowed to
do that even though you're not putting it on the fire. ולא
יפקיענה בסודרין V'lo yafki'enah b'sudarim and you also should not basically crack
it over, heat it up,
like a handkerchief, a
cloth, and it'll fry on the cloth and
presumably, although it's not said in the משנה, Mishnah the גמרא gemara
assumes that this is talking about a cloth that's been heated in
the sun. And this is the principle that there's a problem of
בישול חמה bishul chamma or תולדות חמה. toldos chamma. You're only not
allowed to cook biblically it's only a prohibition if you cook over
a fire. If you cook in the sun, it is not a
problem. What if you cook with something that's been heated by the
fire? Well, the first case in the משנה mishna is heated by
a fire, you've got your hot water pot that's on the fire
heated by a fire. That's a problem. What about if something's been
heated by the sun? So if you can cook in the sun,
you should say you should certainly be allowed to cook in something
heated by the sun. So biblically of course that's true, but rabbinically
they were concerned that something that was heated by the sun is
indistinguishable from something heated by the fire because you don't see what
the original source of heat is, you just see that this is
absorbed heat. So therefore the rabbis would not let you, although they'll
let you fry an egg on the sidewalk directly in the sunlight,
they won't let you fry an egg on a heated up
cloth that's been heated by the sun because then you don't know
where that cloth has been heated. And therefore it says you cannot
do that in this heated cloth. רבי יוסי מתיר Rabbi Yossi matir
but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi allows you to do it in something
heated by the sun. Now by the way in Israel, they have
the דוד שמש, dud shemesh, which is water heated by the sun,
which they use on שבת Shabbat and the big question there is
when you get the sun's rays and then you sort of like,
focus them and they're bouncing off of these panels or whatever, because
a דוד שמש dud shemesh it does not convert the sun's rays
to
electricity. Refocusing the sun's rays and therefore that's using heated by the
sun. But heated by something that absorbed the heat of the sun,
that's a rabbinic problem and even there Rabbi Yose allows. Now I
should say what is the difference between fire and sun in terms
of this? So it could be just like a formal הלכה, cooking
is defined by fire, that's just the way it is, some things
have like formal definitions, end of story. Or you could say no,
it's because it's the normal way to cook by fire, it's not
the normal way to cook by the sun. What's a נפקא מינה?
nafka mina? Let's say you find a normal way to cook that
does not use fire. So what about microwave? So רב משה, Rav
Moshe, now you could say microwave is not a normal way to
cook, it's a normal way to
reheat, I'm not, you can cook by microwave, I'm aware of that,
but it's not so normal, it's more of a normal way to
reheat, maybe people will disagree. Anyway, רב משה Rav Moshe says that
it is based about normal use and he claims that microwave would
actually be בישול דאורייתא. bishul de-oraita. That's what רב משה Rav Moshe
says. A lot of
פוסקים poskim disagree and they say it, you know, A, you could
argue is microwave even normal, but B, they also have the question
about whether it's, like I said, about whether it's a formal distinction
or not, and they say, you know, fire is the definition, end
of story. There's another thing also that they've invented, which is for
travelers, they've got this stuff that you get these like packs of,
I don't know, somehow it's, what is that?
It's some kind of chemical,
right, and then you pull some tab and chemicals mix and that
creates, generates heat and it heats it up, so there also's a
question, you created a chemical reaction but it's not fire and it
generates heat, is that going to be a problem, is that going
to be a בישול bishul problem as well? So anyway, there are
these questions, I would say more simply it's about fire, it's not
about normal versus not normal, and anyway the proof in the pudding
is that all these other things, microwaves and chemicals, are not doing
such a good job cooking, so you could argue anyway that it's
not the normal use regardless, but that is a question of what's
the line of distinction. Yes?
I've also seen solar reflective ovens where they have reflector panels to
concentrate.
So basically like a דוד שמש. dud shemesh. Yes. Yeah, so then
that should be תולדות חמה, toldot chama, that should technically be okay.
All right, so let's continue, so that's the debate presumably although the
משנה Mishnah does not make it clear that's what's going to go
on with the cloth, that's how the גמרא gemara explains it that
it's absorbed heat by the sun and that's the debate of whether
we forbid that although we allow direct sunlight, direct sun cooking. ולא
יטמיננה בחול ובאבק דרכים, Velo yatminena bechol uv'avak drachim,
do not take your egg and bury it in the sand or
in the dust
of the ways of the paths and then the hot sand will
cause it to cook and again that's something heated by the sun.
But interestingly here Rabbi Yose does not disagree and the גמרא Gemara,
will want to understand בשביל שתצלה bishvil she-titzale in order that it
should fry, but again the גמרא Gemara will try to understand why
Rabbi Yose does not disagree here since it seems like it should
be the same case. מעשה שעשו אנשי טבריה, Ma'ase she-asu anshei Tiveria,
there's a story about the people of Tiberias, והביאו סילון של צונן
לתוך אמה של חמים, ve-hevi'u silon shel tzonen le-toch ama shel chamim,
they brought a pipe carrying cold water
into
a canal
of hot water, now this canal of hot water presumably was from
חמי טבריה, chamei Tiveria, from the hot springs of Tiberias. Now חמי
טבריה chamei Tiveria are assumed to be תולדות חמה, toldot chama, not
תולדות אור. toldot ur. By the way, the word is אור, ur,
אלף ואו שורוק, aleph vav shuruk, whatever, אור, ur, not אור, or,
because אור כשדים, Ur Kasdim, אור or means light, אור ur means
fire. Okay, so anyway, so אור, ur, תולדות האור toldot ha-ur is
something derived from a flame, תולדות החמה toldot ha-chama is derived from
a
sun. So although the חמי טבריה chamei Tiveria are not heated by
the sun, the point is they're not heated by a flame, anything
that's not אור ur is in the חמה chama category. Okay, cooking
is defined by flame and therefore חמי טבריה chamei Tiveria are considered
waters that have their heat from חמה, chama, meaning from non-flame. So
therefore what they did is they passed this pipe of cold water
through some, you know, body of water that was hot springs of
Tiberias, so that was like heating up the cold water with תולדות
החמה, toldot ha-chama, okay, which according to the rabbis is a problem
from תולדות החמה, toldot ha-chama, so even though biblically it's not a
problem, it's a rabbinic problem. And מה אמרו להם mah amru lahem
and the rabbis said to the people of Tiberias חכמים chakhamim
the sages said to them אם בשבת im be-shabbat if you did
this on Shabbat כחמים שהוחמו בשבת ke-chamim she-huchmu be-shabbat you have to
treat the water like you heated it up on Shabbat like you
put it on the flame on Shabbat, we're going to be strict.
ואסורין ברחיצה ובשתייה Ve-asurin birchitza u-bishtiya and what's the story about water
that you cooked on Shabbat? You can't use it to wash. wash
your face or to wash yourself and you can't use it to
drink, it's מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. אם ביום טוב, Im b'Yom Tov,
if you did it on יום טוב, Yom Tov, כחמין שהוחמו ביום
טוב, K'chamim shehuchmu b'Yom Tov, it's like water you heated up on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now water you're allowed to heat up on
יום טוב Yom Tov for drinking purposes, so then it's אסור ברחיצה
ומותר בשתייה. assur b'rechitza u'muttar b'shtiya. You can't heat it up for
bathing purposes. Now that seems a little strange. Why can't you? I
mean, isn't bathing a good use for like something that's a common
use? It's like it's a bodily need and so on? Well, we'll
talk about that in the גמרא, Gemara but for now the גמרא
Gemara. is saying that water heated up on יום טוב Yom Tov
cannot be used for bathing, even though it can be used for
drinking. So what do we learn from here? We learn that normally,
if it were just to tell us that this is like תולדות
החמה toldo's hachama and you're not allowed to use it, fine, we
already knew that. But here they're going one step further. They're saying
if you did heat something up with תולדות החמה, toldo's hachama, and
notice by the way, presumably they did this ערב שבת, erev Shabbos,
they put this pipe, they laid this pipe ערב שבת. erev Shabbos.
So here what is the consequence if you did heat something up
with תולדות החמה? toldo's hachama? Are we going to, you know like
yesterday, we said what's the consequence if you left something on the
flame ערב שבת? erev Shabbos? Are you allowed to benefit from it
or not? How much did we forbid the result of it? You
know, what it produced? So here we're saying if you heated it
up you can't benefit from it and not only that, I mean
you have to treat it like you actually cooked it on, like
you actually heated it up on directly on a flame. And not
only that, this משנה Mishnah sounds even if you did it ערב
שבת erev Shabbos and you laid the whole pipe ערב שבת, erev
Shabbos, it's a problem. So here we're pretty strict about what is
the status of this water after the fact. We'll discuss it in
the גמרא Gemara whether that would always be a story about something
you did with תולדות החמה toldo's hachama or we're particularly strict here
for reasons that we will see. Okay, but they were very strict
not only about not liking the having you know heating up with
the חמי טבריה chamei Tverya but even about the status of the
water. Let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara, So the
גמרא Gemara, first turns itself to the first case of the משנה
Mishnah about cooking an egg by the side of this hot water
pot.
איבעיא להו, Iba'ye l'hu, says the גמרא, Gemara they asked. גלגל מהו?
Gilgel mai? Let's say you actually בדיעבד bedieved went ahead and you
cooked your egg by putting it by the side of the water
pot. What's the status? Right, like what's how bad of a transgression
is this? So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, גלגל חייב חטאת. gilgel chayav chatas. You've actually violated שבת
Shabbos biblically. Now this is, I should say there's another גמרא, Gemara
well, there
it's not at all clear from the משנה Mishnah, that's the case.
The simple, which is why the גמרא Gemara asked, you could have
said rabbinically don't do it. And actually I will point out that
there's a major debate in the ראשונים: Rishonim: when is it considered
to be a biblical act of cooking? The רמב"ן Ramban says, based
on the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, a very reasonable position, that you only transgress
cooking דאורייתא d'Oraisa if it's directly on the flame. Once it's not
on the flame, even if it's boiling hot and removed just removed
from the flame, it's not cooking. Classic cooking is directly over a
flame, not on things removed from a flame. Okay, what he does
with this גמרא Gemara I'm not exactly clear. But now you understand
why the גמרא Gemara asked the question. You didn't put it on
a flame, you just put it on the side of a pot,
and the pot is on the flame. Is that real cooking דאורייתא?
d'Oraisa? And at least רב יוסף's Rav Yosef answer is yes. Okay,
now let's take a look. אמר מר בריה דרבינא, Amar Mar b'rei
d'Ravina, said מר Mar the son of רבינא, Ravina, תנינא נמי הכי,
Tanyan nami hachi, we taught similarly in the משנה, Mishnah top of
ל"ח עמוד א': lamed cheis amud aleph: כל שבא בחמין מלפני השבת,
Kol sheba b'chamin milifnei haShabbos,
anything that was cooked before שבת, Shabbos, literally it means came into
hot water, but it presumably means that it was cooked in hot
water, it was cooked before שבת, Shabbos, שורין אותו בחמין בשבת, shorin
oso b'chamin b'Shabbos, you can re-submerge it on שבת Shabbos in hot
water. So this would be the principle being read this way of
אין בישול אחר בישול. ein bishul achar bishul. Once it was cooked
before שבת, Shabbos, no problem about re-submerging it in boiling hot water
on שבת. Shabbos. אין בישול אחר בישול, Ein bishul achar bishul, it's
not cooking once it's already been cooked. וכל שלא בא בחמין מלפני
השבת, V'chol shelo ba b'chamin milifnei haShabbos, if it hasn't been cooked
before שבת, Shabbos, מדיחין אותו בחמין בשבת, madichin oso b'chamin b'Shabbos, you
can rinse it with hot water on שבת, Shabbos, like you can
pour hot water on it, אבל, aval, but you cannot actually submerge
it. Submerging it in hot water would be cooking. Pouring hot water
on it just to heat it up or to rinse get rid
of like the the salt that you would put on to preserve,
that would not be an act of cooking. Okay,
חוץ מן המליח ישן וקולייס האיספנין, chutz min hamaliach yashan v'kolyas ha'ispanin,
except for things that have been like salted for a long time
and this קולייס האיספנין, kolyas ha'ispanin, I have no idea what that
is. What is it? A fish? Some type of a fish. Okay,
that's all it says, fish. I mean רש"י Rashi says דג שקורין
טונינא. dag shekorei tunina. Right, but but it sounds like it's a
fish prepared in a particular way. It doesn't say there, שוין אלט?
shoyn alt?
It says here "old salted fish".
Old salted fish. Okay, there you go, your your herring. What? Maybe
salt cod. Salted cod. Okay. It's a colias fish, a colias mackerel,
scomber colias, imported from...
okay. Anyway, so you have these types of things and in these
cases שהדחתן זו היא גמר מלאכתן, she'hadachasan zo hi gmar melachtan, in
these cases when you pour hot water on it, it actually makes
it fit to be eaten. גמר מלאכתן Gmar melachtan is the end
of the process and in those cases, the משנה Mishnah, just says
you're...
But the גמרא's Gemara assuming
since it uses
the phrase גמר מלאכתן, gmar melachtan, the end of the process, it
echoes like גמר, gmar, like מכה בפטיש, makeh b'patish, גמר מלאכה, gmar
melacha, sounds like the word especially the word מלאכה, melacha, like you've
really biblically transgressed, שמע מינה, shma mina, so you see it from
there. What do you see from it? So first of all, even
that is not פשט pshat in the משנה, Mishnah. not necessarily clear
in the משנה. Mishnah The גמרא Gemara later, there's a משנה Mishnah
way later, you see it on קמ"ה, kuf mem hey, says and
what happens if you actually did pour hot water on these fish?
So then the same רב יוסף Rav Yosef says חייב חטאת. chayav
chatas. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef reads both in our משנה Mishnah
by the egg and that משנה Mishnah, by the fish חייב חטאת.
chayav chatas. You could have just read there rabbinic problems, not דאורייתא
d'oraita problems. Okay, now both of those share the characteristic that they
are not being done directly over heat, right? One is pouring hot
water on it, certainly not directly on the fire, and the other
is against a hot pot, not directly over heat, and these משניות
Mishnayos say don't do it, but it's רב יוסף Rav Yosef who
comes along and says it would actually be a biblical prohibition. Okay,
and it's not at all obvious that that is the case, but
that's רב יוסף's Rav Yosef read of it. Now presumably from there
most ראשונים Rishonim understand against the רמב"ם Rambam that you can actually
do בישול דאורייתא, bishul d'oraita, cooking
דאורייתא, d'oraita, even if it's not directly over the flame, because in
both of these cases it wasn't directly over the flame. One it
was against something heated by the flame and the other it's actually
even it's poured out of something, it's poured so it's not even
in the original pot that was on the fire, and in both
of those cases it's possible to get בישול דאורייתא bishul d'oraita and
this becomes a category that we're going to see pretty soon in
the few days called like, again most ראשונים Rishonim against רמב"ם, Rambam,
called קלי הבישול, kalei habishul, things that cook very easily like an
egg or these types of salted fish can cook not even over
a flame, not maybe even in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, maybe
even in a כלי שני, kli sheni, maybe even in, the whole
issue about tea and you need to make it three times is
because things that maybe cook easily maybe it's considered בישול דאורייתא bishul
d'oraita even if it's not only not on a flame but not
even in the original vessel that was on the flame. And that
would be the case of like the pouring here by the fish
or by the egg against this thing. So most ראשונים Rishonim read
this, which is the פשט pshat that it's possible to cook something
even not on the flame, maybe not even in the first vessel
the כלי ראשון. kli rishon. Now I should point out, and that's
the proof, look in both these cases not on the flame and
it's still a problem. דאורייתא? D'oraita? Not clear. Now I should point
out that the phrase גמר מלאכתן gmar melachtan suggests something that's other
than cooking. גמר מלאכה Gmar melacha suggests a different category called מכה
בפטיש, makeh b'patish, that you're not allowed to do anything on שבת
Shabbat that's the end of a process. So you can't do the
final hammer bang on something to like finish it off even if
it itself is not a מלאכה melacha but if it finishes the
object. And this suggests, sounds like, that the same can be true
by food, that if you finish the process of making food even
not through an act of cooking you could be חייב chayav because
of מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish because of גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. Now
the בבלי Bavli pretty much completely rejects this and the פוסקים poskim
reject this and you never hear this stated in the בבלי, Bavli,
but ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says it. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says that
you can be, that you can do גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, מכה
בפטיש makeh b'patish by food, which then raises a big problem because
all the types of things that you thought you were exempt with
like בישול חמה bishul chama and all these other tech ways in
which you thought you're not cooking, well why aren't you חייב chayav
because of מכה בפטיש? makeh b'patish? So you have to find an
answer to that. But the ירושלמי Yerushalmi does say you can have
מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish if you finish the process of making food
and making it edible even if it doesn't involve cooking. The בבלי
Bavli seems to ignore that and therefore the basic way this is
read, the pouring of the hot water or the egg, is read
that it's בישול bishul not מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish and that at
least we're learning that בישול bishul applies even when it's not directly
on the fire or not in a כלי ראשון. kli rishon.
Yes, in the case with salted fish, you're not, the cooking is
by salting it. Right, you rinse it off, that's completing the process
and making it edible.
Right, so that's exactly what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says is that it's
not really about cooking in the terms of using the hot water,
it's really about finishing a process that's not about cooking at all.
So that's the read that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi gives, which is a
very reasonable read, and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has a couple of examples
like that where you're basically processing something and you're finishing it not
by cooking but by doing some other, look there's a lot of
dishes that we can make that are like cold, you know, and
you finish it, you know, you could I don't know make who
knows you
let's say you make some type of a sauce or something, you
add a lot of things and you stir it all together, now
you've finished something even without any heat at all. So that's what
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says. Luckily the בבלי Bavli doesn't say that explicitly
and the פוסקים poskim reject that or else that would be much
more restrictive. But that is the פשט pshat of this משנה, Mishnah.
there's no question that that's the פשט pshat of this משנה.
Mishnah, But also rinsing the fish with hot water completes it, but
what about cold water?
Right, so in theory according to this even if it were cold
water, but again the בבלי Bavli and the ראשונים Rishonim of the
בבלי Bavli primarily read this that it's cooking and therefore they limit
it to hot water, they limit it to יד סולדת בו yad
soledes bo water and they try to fit it into
the. They'd say like מזיגת הכוס, mezigas hakos, right?
You see, it's not considered drinkable till I add my three fifths
water, is that not considered
גמר מלאכה gmar melacha according to ירושלמי Yerushalmi or what have you?
I can show you the cases in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, I think
a number of them don't involve any, if I remember, a number
of them don't involve any type of heat at all. They involve
chopping and stuffing and these types of things. So how far it
would go, it's not clear. They definitely are talking about like a
major process with multiple steps. I don't know if they would talk
about something as trivial as adding water. But I'll bring in tomorrow,
I'll bring you the examples that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has about it.
Okay, let's move on. So that's about... so very critical things being
principles being laid here about what constitutes cooking. So number one is
according to the בבלי Bavli read at least, even not on the
fire, even maybe in a כלי שני kli sheini or, you know,
pouring from a כלי ראשון kli rishon and so on. So very
important principle number one. Now we get to things that are heated
by the sun. ולא יפקיענו בסודרין, V'lo yafkienu b'sudarin, do not fry
it in some heated up type of a cloth. והדתנן, V'ha-detnan, that
which we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, again from about a hundred
pages from
now, נותנין תבשיל לתוך הבור Notnin tavshil l'soch habor בשביל שישתמר, bishvil
she-yishtamer, you can put a cooked thing
into a pit in order to protect it, either keep it cool
or protect it from the animals, ואת המים היפים ברעים, V'es hamayim
hayafim birayim, or good sweet water, good water into bad water, בשביל
שיצטננו, bishvil she-yitzatanenu, it should cool off. Presumably it means in some
type of a container, so you lower it into a, you know,
low down into a well to get it cool even if the
water is not good that's around it. But okay, it's like a
type of refrigeration. So none of that is a big חידוש. chiddush.
But here comes the חידוש. chiddush. ואת הצונן בחמה, V'es hatzonan bachamah,
you can put cold water into the sun בשביל שיחמו bishvil she-yeichamu
that it should heat up. So you see that it's okay to
heat things in the sun. I already gave you the answer, but
here the גמרא Gemara is assuming that the rabbis wouldn't allow even
directly in the sun. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא רבי יוסי
ולא רבנן, Leima Rabbi Yosi v'lo Rabbanan, maybe that's רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi who's okay with the heated cloth, only he would allow you
to heat things up in the sun? So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman no. בחמה Bachamah directly in the
sun דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי, dekuli alma lo pligi deshari, everybody
says that's fine. בתולדות האור, Betoldos ha-ur, again אור ur not "or",
in something that is derivative of heat of like fire, דכולי עלמא
לא פליגי דאסיר, dekuli alma lo pligi de-asir, everybody agrees that's forbidden.
That's the case of the egg by the side of the pot.
Not only forbidden, it could even be דאורייתא d'Oraisa under some circumstances.
כי פליגי, Ki pligi, what's the debate? בתולדות חמה, Betoldos chamah, something
that has been literally a child of the sun, something that has
heat derived from the sun, absorbed heat from the sun. Biblically it's
nothing, but rabbinically it's hard to distinguish that case from something that
has absorbed heat from fire. So in that case they debate. מר
סבר גזרינן Mar savar gazrinan תולדות חמה אטו תולדות האור. toldos chamah
atu toldos ha-ur. The rabbis say you can't use something that has
absorbed heat from the sun because then it'll be easily confused with
absorbed heat from the fire. So therefore this cloth that has absorbed
heat from the sun is no good. Even though the sun itself
is okay? The sun itself is okay. Right, so it's biblically it's
totally okay and the sun is obvious that it's different. But this
is not obviously different. So therefore you can't use it. ומר סבר
ורבי יוסי לא גזרינן, U-mar savar v'Rabbi Yosi lo gazrinan, no, I'm
not gonna make those types of גזירות gzeiros and as long as
it's coming from the sun directly or indirectly it is fine. Okay,
now we get onto the next case about not burying it in
the heated sand where fine, but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi? doesn't disagree.
No one paskens like רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosi No. ולא יטמיננו בחול,
V'lo yatminenu bachol, do not bury it in the sand. So why
does... why does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi not disagree? וליפלוג נמי רבי
יוסי בהא, V'liflog nami Rabbi Yosi beha, why doesn't רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi also
disagree with this? רבה אמר Rabbah amar גזירה שמא יטמין ברמץ, gzeirah
shema yatmin b'remetz, we're afraid that you're gonna bury it in in
ashes. What is this? We're going to see, one of the things
we have not yet dealt with is a separate גזירה, gzeirah, not
of leaving stuff on the flame from before שבת, Shabbos, but הטמנה,
hatmanah, putting stuff in, surrounding it with, you know, material that will
keep, retain its heat or add. Okay, and this they did not
want you to do for similar reason they didn't want you to
put stuff on the flame before שבת. Shabbos. Why did you not
put on the flame before שבת? Shabbos? You'll come to stir the
flame. So don't put it in stuff that will add heat before
שבת Shabbos like, because you'll come why, let's say it's I don't
know, let's say it's add heat like this this hot sand. Okay,
so what's the big deal? So what am I... what will I
do if I put it that way before שבת? Shabbos? No, because
if you start, if we allow you to put in stuff that
will add heat, you surround it with that stuff, the best thing
that'll add heat is ashes that have a lot of retained heat
in it. So you'll bury it in ashes before שבת Shabbos and
then because the ashes have retained heat you might come to stir
the ashes. So because the same way we don't want you to
put it on an uncovered flame before שבת, Shabbos, we don't want
you to bury it in ashes before שבת Shabbos and once we
don't want you to bury it in ashes, we broaden that and
say we don't want you to bury it in any type of
a thing that adds heat, even, you know, even before שבת. Shabbos.
Okay, so therefore the sand is something that like it at... ah,
sand is something that... you can't stir to raise the heat in
any way, it's only from the sun. Nevertheless, part of this category,
even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi agrees that the category of burying something
in things that add heat, even if the only real concern is
the ashes, we broadened the category.
Even though no ashes
around. What? Even though no ashes around.
Even though no ashes around, we have broadened the category. So even
if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi say you want to do it on
a handkerchief, on some type of a cloth, fine. But you want
to bury it in some material that adds heat, even if it's
only absorbed from the sun, that's part of the גזירה gezirah of
not doing הטמנה, hatmanah, and there רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, agrees. Yes.
Burying food in hot coals is still to this day a very
common method of cooking in much of the world.
Okay, of cooking or retaining heat? Of cooking, interesting. Actual cooking. Right,
very interesting. And here it was just, right, so here and that
was part of the issue here as well, that you're burying it
maybe to retain the heat but maybe you also want to finish
the cooking, and it's those concerns. Now so that's right, now there
is a whole question which I'm not going to get to now,
which is רש״י Rashi tries to conflate the idea of putting something
in an oven with a to say that that's part of the
גזירה gezirah of burying something, you know, in the coals. All the
other ראשונים rishonim disagree, they say there's oven and then there's coals.
But they want to know why can you put something in an
oven? Why isn't that like הטמנה hatmanah in the ashes? You can't
do הטמנה hatmanah in the ashes, but you can put something in
an oven and with a covered fire which is at least as
hot and as likely to be stirred as ashes and so on.
So they make a technical distinction that covering something in ashes is
only when the covering or covering something in things that retain the
heat touches all sides of the vessel, and only then is this
גזירה gezirah of הטמנה hatmanah of burying something. So although it's in
an oven and it's surrounded by the oven walls, but the oven
walls and the heat thing are not touching the vessel itself. Okay,
so that raises questions, you know, people want to put a hot
a towel over the food that's on the hot plate to retain
the heat, so as long as it doesn't touch all sides, it's
okay because it's very hard the way the ראשונים rishonim limit הטמנה,
hatmanah, it's very hard to be עובר over on it because it
has to actually touch all of the sides. The issue I raised
before about the about the crockpot, right, some people want to say,
oh, to get a בלעך blech for a crockpot, you have to
line it with tin foil to do an additional covering. But you
line it with tin foil, now when you put it in, it's
held very snugly on all sides, and they'll say, well, that's הטמנה.
hatmanah. And then the question for הטמנה hatmanah comes, does it have
to also cover the the roof? Maybe it's not הטמנה hatmanah because
it's only covering, you know, the the sides and the bottom, but
it's not actually covering the roof. So anyway. They cover the sides
or they have ceramic insert? Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so anyway but this is the question about הטמנה. hatmanah.
We'll see more of that, but that's what we're saying the problem
is here, that even רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi who's okay with תולדות
חמה, toldos chama, agrees that there's a rabbinic category of הטמנה hatmanah
which is sourced in the case of the ashes, but then it
expands to anything that adds heat. Yes. They make clothes, these heavy
clothes that you put on
top of a טשולנט cholent pot or a hot or a hot
water urn or a whatever, and so why is that okay? You're
covering it to retain the heat.
Right,
so as long as it doesn't sort of surround it completely around
on all sides.
But it does.
No, it all the way
around on a let's say an oval or a circular thing. Right,
it it does cover. It doesn't it doesn't go to the bottom.
And does it also go to the top or just goes to
the side?
On a small pot, it goes on all sides.
Like including the top? I understand.
It's like a jacket. It's on the top. You put it on
the top and it
it folds down around whatever shape you're putting it on. Oh I
see. It goes around.
It's not buried.
Yeah, no, but no, well that's.
They make it especially for for שבת, Shabbat,
it says שבת Shabbat or something on, yeah.
Heavy clothes
and it goes on the top and on all the sides?
Very well. New thing for me. Maybe
if it's rectangular, it's not a square.
Well, it's because it's because it's snug. Well, the question is that
here also, it's.
It's
not snug.
Oh, it's not snug.
But it covers.
So probably because it's not snug. I mean, like I said, we
have defined הטמנה hatmanah almost out of existence, okay? Because it's like
only when it's like really snug and really on all sides. Let's
let's hold off on more discussions of הטמנה hatmanah when we get
to when we get to the משניות mishnayot of it, okay? Let's
hold off a little bit. But anyway, but that is the category.
So let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So it says like this, מה, ma, okay, that's what רבא Rava
says, גזירה שמא יטמין ברמץ. gezirah shema yatmin beremetz. Let me look
at the דף. רבי יוסף Rabbi Yosef אמר מפני שמזיז עפר ממקומו.
mipnei shemeiziz afar mimkomo. No, it's a separate problem. The problem here
is according to רבי יוסף, Rabbi Yosef, mean according to the rabbis
it's obvious the problem is just that it's heated by the sun,
but according to רבי יוסף Rabbi Yosef the problem is is that
when you put it in the dirt, you're moving the dirt. So
what? So רש״י Rashi says is you're making a hole in the
dirt, and it's a problem about חופר גומא, chofer guma, like you
know, you can't make a hole because it's like a בונה boneh
or חורש. choresh. תוספות Tosafot says it's a מוקצה muktzeh problem, you're
putting it in the dirt and you're moving the dirt. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו, mai beinayhu, what's a difference? איכא
בינייהו עפר תיחוח, icha beinayhu afar tichuach, where it's pre-dug. And it's
loose dirt. So therefore, it's still a problem of burying of הטמנה
hatmanah because you're still burying it in something that adds heat, but
it's not a problem of either מוקצה muktzeh because it's been pre-dug
and maybe it's sort of set aside for that purpose, and it's
not a problem about making a hole because the hole also is
like relatively already there or it won't stand, as soon as you
remove the pot, it'll fall back into place, and therefore it's okay.
מיתיבי, Meiteivei, I'll ask against this. רבן גמליאל אומר Rabban Gamliel omer
מגלגלין ביצה על גבי גג רותח, megalgelin beitzah al gabei gag roteiach,
you can fry an egg on top of a boiling hot roof.
There you go. ואין מגלגלין ביצה על גבי סיד רותח, ve'ein megalgelin
beitzah al gabei sid roteiach, but not on boiling hot plaster. Now
presumably, the plaster is boiling because it was heated up by a
fire. Apparently, that's how they would make plaster. So presumably, the גמרא
Gemara assumes the difference is that the sun is תולדות חמה, toldos
chamah, which is okay, and the plaster is תולדות האור, toldos ha'ur,
which is no good. So בשלמא למאן דאמר—so bishlama leman de'amar we
want to understand why the roof is not a problem, why רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi, also agrees that the roof is a problem. So
בשלמא למאן דאמר גזירה שמא יטמין ברמץ—if bishlama leman de'amar gezeirah shema
yatmin beremetz the reason that רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi if the reason
of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, agreeing to the case of the dirt
was because it was like burying it, a הטמנה, hatmanah, so the
roof isn't a הטמנה, hatmanah, you're not burying it, you're just putting
it on the roof. So we understand why at least if this
was going according to
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi why רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would be okay
with the roof because you're not burying it. אלא למאן דאמר מפני
שמזיז עפר ממקומו, ela leman de'amar mipnei shemeiziz afar mimekomo, if the
concern is that you're moving dirt and you're maybe making a hole
or you're maybe making, you know, you're making a—moving מוקצה, muktzeh, so
לגזור, ligzor, that could be even a roof should be no good
because presumably their roofs, they were assuming sometimes would have dirt on
them. So although you're not burying it in the dirt, you might
be at least making a hole or moving the dirt. So why
isn't—why would this be okay? Even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. should have
a problem if it's on the roof. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, סתם גגות לית בהו עפר. stam gagot leit behu afar. No,
roofs don't have dirt and we're not concerned. A roof, okay, fine.
So anyways, so presumably though we're saying that this works according to
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi Presumably the rabbis wouldn't like this either because
it's תולדות חמה, toldos chamah, but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would be
okay because you're not burying it in the sand, you're not moving
dirt. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. מעשה שעשו אנשי טבריא,
ma'aseh she'asu anshei Teverya, our משנה, Mishnah that the people of Tiberias
did, והביאו סילון של צונן לתוך אמה של חמין, vehevi'u silon shel
tzonan letoch amah shel chamin, they took the pipe of cold water
into the—into the, you know, whatever it was—what did we say? The
channel of hot water, etc. Now we understand that this is a
type of a—like what's the problem here, especially if they did it
ערב שבת? erev Shabbos? If you did it on שבת, Shabbos, you're
cooking—you're—you're heating something up with תולדות חמה, toldos chamah, but what's about
ערב שבת? erev Shabbos? So we assume that the problem is that
this is a type of הטמנה. hatmanah. The same way you can't
put your pot and put it into the hot ashes or in
the hot sand, you can't put your
water—bury it into the hot water. Okay, so it's a type of
like a הטמנה hatmanah problem. That's conceptually how we're understanding what the
problem was. So and again, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi did not disagree
with this, so presumably רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi agrees that this is
the problem of הטמנה. hatmanah. So let's take a look.
בשלמא למאן דאמר גזירה שמא יטמין ברמץ, bishlama leman de'amar gezeirah shema
yatmin beremetz, if it's a concern of putting it into hot ashes,
היינו דדמי להטמנה. hainu dedami lehatmanah. We understand: don't put it into
hot ashes, don't put water into this other water. We understand why
it's a problem. We also understand why they gave him a hard
time even though it was ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, because הטמנה hatmanah
is something you're not allowed to do ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. If
it was just using תולדות חמה, toldos chamah, that's only a problem
on שבת, Shabbos, right? But this is something they did ערב שבת.
erev Shabbos. So why are the rabbis give him a hard time?
Because הטמנה hatmanah is you're not allowed to put the food in
this hot stuff even ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, and that's what the
issue was. מוסיף הבל, mosif hevel, it adds heat. Okay. אלא למאן
דאמר מפני שמזיז עפר ממקומו, ela leman de'amar mipnei shemeiziz afar mimekomo,
according to the one that says the whole issue is like a
מוקצה muktzeh issue or making a hole issue, מאי איכא למימר? mai
ika lemeimar? What's bothering them with this whole טבריא? Teverya? Why is
this a case where—meaning רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi shouldn't have a problem
here, right? Because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi only had a problem with
the sand because he was moving sand. Well, this isn't moving מוקצה
muktzeh or making a hole. What would—why would רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
have a problem with what they did in טבריא? Teverya? So גמרא
says, okay, maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi doesn't have a problem. וסברת
מעשה טבריא אסיפא קאי? vesavrat ma'aseh Teverya aseifa kai? Why do you
think that it's going on the second part of the משנה where
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi himself agrees that certain things are a problem,
and that implicitly רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi agrees that the Tiberias case
was problematic? No, ארישא קאי. areisha kai. It's going on the first
part; it's a debate between רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and the rabbis.
לא יטמננה בסודרין—do lo yatminena besudarim not use things that have absorbed
heat from the sun like a cloth—רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi מתיר—רבי יוסי
allows it. והכי קאמרי ליה רבנן לרבי יוסי—so vehachi kaamri lei rabanan
leRabbi Yossi this case of Tiberias is not something רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi: would agree with. Here's what the rabbis are saying to רבי
יוסי: How can you say you have a problem that—that it's okay
things with absorbed heat from the sun? המעשה דאנשי טבריא דתולדות חמה
היא ואסרו להו רבנן hama'aseh de'anshei Teverya detoldos chamah hi ve'asru lehu
rabanan how about the case of Tiberias? That was not heat from
a fire, that was heat from a sun, or not a sun,
but anyway, not from a fire, and that was a problem. So
you see that even when it's not from a fire, there's a
problem. That's the story of Tiberias. אמר להו Amru lehu so the
rabbis said so he said back to the rabbis: No, you know
why Tiberias was a problem? He told us אור הוא Or hu
that actually is heated from a fire. Why is it heated from
a fire?
דחלפי אפיתחא דגיהנם. Dechalfei apitcha d'Gehinnom. Where do you think the water
gets, where do you think the hot springs of Tiberias get hot?
It's because they make a... they pass by Gehinnom on their way,
they come from way down and they pass by Gehinnom and they
get the fires of Gehinnom and that's why they're hot. So, what
is the Gemara saying? The Gemara is saying like this. Rabbi
Yose is silent at the end of the Mishna. So we're assuming
he agrees. Why does he agree with the hot sand? That we
said might be because it's like הטמנה Hatmanah or might be because
it's a concern of moving sand. So how do you deal with
the case of Tiberias? Well if it's like הטמנה, Hatmanah, that's also
like הטמנה. Hatmanah. But if the הטמנה Hatmanah issue is not your
issue, why does Rabbi Yose agree? And the Gemara says, he doesn't
really agree, or he agrees for a different reason. He would explain
the Tiberias case as תולדות אור, Toldos or, but you actually are
right that he would not consider it a type of a הטמנה.
Hatmanah. So there's this question about A, why Rabbi Yose agrees by
sand, but B, what the problem was by Tiberia. Was Tiberia a
problem because it was like הטמנה, Hatmanah, or was Tiberia a problem
because it was a תולדות החמה Toldos hachamah by itself or תולדות
אור? Toldos or? And the reason it's more sort of seems more
to be read like a הטמנה Hatmanah issue, why that has a
greater, sort of you know, seems like a better reason, is because
it seems like this was done ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and the
rabbis still had a problem on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. Now, not
necessarily. What you could say is, is that you had the pipe
was there from ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, but they turned it on
and the water flowed on שבת Shabbos and got heated on שבת.
Shabbos. Right? You understand? It's not exactly clear when did the water
get heated up. Right? They laid the pipe ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos,
but the water maybe was heated up on שבת. Shabbos. So that's
the question: why is the Mishna giving them such a hard time?
One way to explain it is because it was ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos and it's like הטמנה Hatmanah and that's an even ערב שבת
Erev Shabbos problem. The other is, forget הטמנה, Hatmanah, they were turning
on the water on שבת, Shabbos, heating it up on שבת, Shabbos,
and even if it was a תולדות החמה, Toldos hachamah, at least
it was a Rabbinic problem. But what's surprising at the end of
the Mishna is not only did they say it was forbidden, they
even made the water after the fact forbidden, that you couldn't even
use the water. Okay, yes.
Here's a question is why are we... why are we assuming Rabbi
Yose wouldn't disagree? Meaning, זה חכמים, Ze Chachamim, you know he disagrees
with the חכמים. Chachamim. And anyway, זה מעשה שהיה, Ze maiseh shehaya,
so it's like he wouldn't dare. It's not like 'I disagree'. Meaning
the חכמים Chachamim said something and, you know, he wasn't there.
Because he introduced his position and then in the end of the
Mishna there was no discussion, so it seems like he doesn't have...
That would be the assumption. Yeah, but you can't disagree with a
מעשה שהיה. Maiseh shehaya.
Yeah, but you could be challenged by a מעשה שהיה Maiseh shehaya
and have to give a response. And that's what the Gemara's saying.
It's missing the response, so the Gemara provides the response. Okay, let's
take a look. אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav Chisda. אמר רב חסדא
מעשה שאסו אנשי טבריא. Amar Rav Chisda: Maiseh she'asu anshei Tverya. Now
in ל"ט ע"ב. Lamed Tes Amud Beis. From what happened in אנשי
טבריא, Anshei Tverya, ואסרו להו רבנן, V'asru lehu rabanan, and the rabbis
said that it was forbidden. So now we're making the point: not
only did they say you're not allowed to heat something to do
this like הטמנה, Hatmanah, or you're not allowed to heat something up
with תולדות חמה, Toldos chamah, they even said the waters were forbidden.
בטלה הטמנה בדבר המוסיף הבל ואפילו מבעוד יום. Batlah hatmanah b'davar hamosif
hevel v'afilu mibod yom. You cannot do הטמנה Hatmanah again, we're comparing
it to הטמנה Hatmanah burying in the water is like burying it
in the sand,
in something that adds heat, right? There's things that just preserve heat,
but there's things that add. You cannot... preserving heat you can do
ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. Take it off the fire and wrap it
in towels. But adding heat you cannot, but you can't do that
on שבת Shabbos itself to preserve heat. We'll talk more about הטמנה.
Hatmanah. But here you're actually adding heat, hot water, hot sand, and
you see you cannot do it even ערב שבת Erev Shabbos if
it adds heat. You cannot do it at even on ערב שבת.
Erev Shabbos. Now Tosafot says, this is a חידוש, Chiddush, like later
there's going to be explicit משניות Mishnayos that you're not allowed to
do הטמנה ערב שבת Hatmanah Erev Shabbos on something that adds heat.
So Tosafot says no, the חידוש Chiddush here is is that you
can't even use the water after the fact. That it's the same
like we discussed yesterday, if you kept soup on an open flame
in violation, you can't eat from it on שבת. Shabbos. Here, if
you did הטמנה Hatmanah in violation, you can't benefit from it on
שבת. Shabbos. So the point is that they didn't let them use
the water, even though it was ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, since it
added heat, you're not allowed to benefit from it even after the
fact. אמר עולא. Amar Ulla. So now Ulla says, הלכה כאנשי טבריא.
Halacha k'anshei Tverya. You know what? We rule like the people of
Tiberias, which is pretty interesting, because the sense you get in the
Mishna is people of Tiberias are like not doing it in any
informed way, they're just doing it. And comes along the rabbis and
say you're making a mistake. But Ulla says, no, you know what,
the people of טבריה Tverya were correct. Now why is it? Is
it that, is it because we're ruling like Rabbi Yose, it's תולדות
החמה? Toldos hachamah? Is it because it's, you know, it's not considered
הטמנה? Hatmanah? You know, a pipe through water is not exactly the
same as normal הטמנה? Hatmanah? Not exactly clear. But he says actually
that would be okay. אמר אמר ליה רב נחמן כבר תברונהו אנשי
טבריה לסילונייהו *Amar lay Rav Nachman kvar tavrunhu anshei Teveryah le-silonayehu*. I'm
sorry, the people of Tiberias have already broken their pipe. Okay? Which,
I don't know how they broke their pipe, but I would say
the rabbis broke their pipe. Anyway, sorry, no, we don't rule like
the people of Tiberias, okay? So what we get from this is
again תולדות החמה *toldos hachamah* is rabbinically prohibited,
and הטמנה *hatmanah*
is something that adds heat you can't even do ערב שבת Erev
Shabbat *erev Shabbos*. Presumably that's what seems the גמרא's *Gemara's* weighing to
say that that's what happens with the pipe, it was considered a
type of הטמנה *hatmanah*, and most significantly, if you violate any of
this stuff, you can't even בדיעבד *bedieved* you can't benefit from the
food. Okay, מעשה שאנסו אנשי טבריה *maaseh she-ansu anshei Teveryah*. So now
we're going to get to the last part which is because we
treat the water as if it was actually heated on שבת Shabbat
*Shabbos* you can't use it for bathing or drinking, and if it
was יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* you can use it for
drinking but not for bathing. And now we're going to get to
a very important הלכות *halachos* about under what circumstances can you use
water on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* for bathing, can you
take a hot shower on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, and
under what circumstances can you use hot water for bathing on שבת
Shabbat *Shabbos* that was heated from before שבת *Shabbos*. For example, when
would you have it heated before שבת *Shabbos*? Well, let's say you're
in an apartment building or let's say you're in a house where,
I'm not going to get to the whole question about, a big
question about when you use hot water does it bring cold water
in and you know is it cooking and whatever. There's scenarios where
you can control. Let's say you're in your home and you totally
control the hot water heater and what you do is you turn
off the fire before שבת *Shabbos* so it won't keep and this
is how at your home you can definitely allow yourself to use
hot water on שבת *Shabbos* is you turn off the hot water
heater before שבת *Shabbos* and you run the cold water, no excuse
me, you run hot water for like I don't know you know
a good while if you take a hot shower for like a
half hour right before שבת *Shabbos*. What does that do? It brings
cold water into the bottom of the hot water heater. So now
when new cold water comes in as you continue to draw hot
water, the new cold water is coming into a layer of cold
water. Right, if you only turn off the fire and then you
use the hot water on שבת *Shabbos*, you'd bring in cold water
it would come into hot water and that would be cooking because
it would be water that was heated יד סולדת בו כלי ראשון
*yad soledes bo kli rishon*. But if you've used took a nice
long half hour hour shower whatever everybody took their hot showers right
before שבת *Shabbos* after you turned the flame off, right, then you
have all this cold water is already there on the bottom, it's
not יד סולדת בו *yad soledes bo* and as new cold water
comes in it's coming into cold water. That's a way you can
definitely use the hot water in your house on שבת *Shabbos*. So
let's say you went ahead and you did that and now, no
because the stuff on the top is still hot. But let's say
you went ahead and you did that and now you want to
take a nice hot bath on שבת *Shabbos* or a nice hot
shower. It was all heated up from before שבת *Shabbos*. What's the
story? Okay, so this is a question. Using hot water that was
preheated on שבת *Shabbos* and using and heating up water on יום
טוב Yom Tov? *Yom Tov* to take a bath. Let's take a
look at the גמרא *Gemara*. We'll just get started with it. מאי
רחיצה *Mai rechitzah*? So what is the bathing that it says, you
know, you cannot bathe with it? It says this water that was
heated on שבת *Shabbos*. It's like water that was heated on שבת
*Shabbos* and you cannot use it for bathing. אילימא רחיצת כל גופו
*Ilima rechitzas kol gufo*, if you want to bathe your entire body,
אלא חמין שהוחמו בשבת הן דאסורין *ela chamin she-huchmu be-Shabbos hen de-asurin*.
You're telling me that water that was heated on שבת *Shabbos* is
forbidden to bathe your whole body. הא חמין שהוחמו מערב שבת מותרין
*Ha chamin she-huchmu me-erev Shabbos mutarin*, which would suggest that if you
heated the hot water before שבת *Shabbos* you could bathe your whole
body. But that's not true. והתניא *Ve-hatanya*, we taught a ברייתא *braisa*,
חמין שהוחמו מערב שבת *chamin she-huchmu me-erev Shabbos*, למחר רוחץ בהן פניו
ידיו ורגליו *le-machar rochetz ba-hen panav yadav ve-raglav*,
you can wash your face and hands, אבל לא כל גופו *aval
lo kol gufo*, you can't wash your whole body. Why not? Because
they were concerned that if we let you bathe your whole body
with preheated water you would come to use water that was heated
on שבת *Shabbos* particularly because they had these Roman bathhouses. So once
you go see and you're going into a bath with heated water
on שבת *Shabbos*, right, so it's very easy next time you go
to the bathhouse where they're actually not heating it from before שבת
*Shabbos* but they're heating it on שבת *Shabbos*. So therefore they did
not, since that was a very common phenomenon taking these hot baths
and very often the water was heated on שבת *Shabbos*, they did
not let you do this. So here, even in the scenario I
gave you where you're allowed to use hot water in your house
on שבת *Shabbos*, you cannot fully immerse your body, you cannot take
a bath in hot water on שבת *Shabbos* because of a גזירת
מרחצאות *gezeiras merchatsaot*, a גזירה *gezeirah* of that you'll come to do
it next time you'll actually with heating the water on שבת *Shabbos*
itself.
You mean you'll heat the water or you'll use somebody else's?
Or you'll use somebody else's heated water, whatever the case is. Okay,
so that is you're not allowed to take an entire hot bath
on שבת *Shabbos* even if the water's been preheated. So when it
says because this water is like it's heated on שבת *Shabbos* you
can't bathe with it, it can't mean you can't bathe your whole
body, that would be forbidden even if it was heated before שבת
*Shabbos*. אלא פניו ידיו ורגליו *Ela panav yadav ve-raglav*. You can't even
use it for your hands and face because then if it was
heated before שבת *Shabbos* you could use it for your hands and
face and feet, but if it was heated on שבת *Shabbos* you
could not. So when the משנה *Mishnah* says this water is like
it's heated on שבת *Shabbos* and you can't use it, it means
you can't even use it for your hands and face. Okay, is
that clear? But now it goes on. It says, ורמינהי *Ur-min-hei*, but
look at the end of the משנה *Mishnah*. ביום טוב *Be-Yom Tov*.
If you use this water that you know this water that passed
through the hot water on יום טוב, Yom Tov כחמין שהוחמו ביום
טוב, ke'chamim shehuchmu beYom Tov, then it's like water heated on יום
טוב, Yom Tov? ואסורין ברחיצה, ve'assurin be'rechitza, you can't bathe with it,
ומותרין בשתייה, u'mutarin bi'shtiya, but you can drink with it. Now what
did we say can't bathe meant? Can't use it for your hands
and feet. So you're telling me you can't heat water on יום
טוב for your hands and feet? Why not? לימא תנן סתמא כבית
שמאי, leima tnan stama keBeis Shammai, is the סתם משנה stam Mishnah
like בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? דתנן בית שמאי אומרים, detnan Beis Shammai
omrim, לא יחם אדם חמין לרגליו, lo yachom adam chamim leraglav, אלא
אם כן ראויים לשתייה. ela im ken reuyim lishtiya.
You cannot heat water even for your hands and feet unless you're
doing it for the sake of drinking it. ובית הלל מתירין uBeis
Hillel matirin and בית הלל Beis Hillel allows it. So we are
now left with the following issue which we will answer tomorrow, which
is
water that you are allowed to use if you heat it ערב
שבת Erev Shabbat but not on שבת is water not for your
whole body but for your hands and face. But that type of
water you should be allowed to heat on יום טוב. So what
is the case of water that you can use for your body
if you did it ערב שבת but not on שבת but you
also cannot use on יום טוב? Okay, and that's what the גמרא
is going to try to figure out tomorrow and also discuss are
there any limitations of heating water for your body on יום טוב
which gets ultimately to the question of can you take a hot
shower on יום טוב? So if you want to find the answer
to that, come back tomorrow. א שיינע טאג.
A sheine tag.